So, the question is on uh
the question is on uh
on uh Vipallasa Sutta,
or um also translated as the uh
inversions.
It's uh Anguttara Nikaya, Book of Fours,
number 49.
Because there are four inversions of
perceptions, inversions of mind, inversions of view.
inversions of mind, inversions of view.
What four?
The inversion of perception,
mind and view that takes impermanent to
be permanent.
Number two, the inversion of perception,
mind, and view
that takes what is suffering to be
pleasurable. Number three, the inversion of
Number three, the inversion of
perception, mind, and view that takes
what is not self to be self.
And number four, the inversion of
perception, mind, and view that takes
what is unattractive to be attractive.
These are the four inversions of
perception, mind, and view.
And there are four non-inversions,
non-inversion that takes impermanent as
impermanent, um
suffering as suffering, uh not self as
not self, and uh unattractive as
unattractive.
So, the first the first inversion of
perception, mind, and view
is uh the inversion of impermanent uh as
permanent. So,
inversion of taking anicca to be nicca.
And um
as we spoke in some previous talks, um
anicca, it
you can translate it as impermanence. Uh
it's absolutely fine.
But it also needs to be understood in a
sense the impermanence needs to be
understood in a sense that um
it's not like a it's not like an a an
impersonal an impersonal observation of uh of
an impersonal observation of uh of
everything is constantly changing.
Thus, nothing is really permanent. The
impermanence refers to the to the sense
of uh self that is attached to the
ownership of things.
That's when you feel
well, that's when you regard things in
uh permanently, which is uh when uh when
those things change, that's when you
feel that impermanence as unpleasant.
Hence, anicca and dukkha are the
characteristics of things. So,
impermanence, anicca, um should be
should be uh understood in the sense of
the yes, uh things are impermanent in
the sense of they're changing, but it's
more like that they're changing out of
out of out outside of the scope of your
own will, of your own control.
Which means things can be pleasing,
agreeable, can obey your will until they
don't. So, it's a recognition that this
um
outer like the what what is inconceivable
like the what what is inconceivable
to access with your intention, with your
will, with your control, that's where
things are rooted in. They're rooted in
that inaccessible, in that which you
cannot control. Thus, they're
impermanent. Because when things change,
and they will, you you won't be able
able to to um foresee it, so to speak.
Even if you expect say you expect
something will change this very second,
when change happens, it's always a
surprise on that existential level. You
cannot see the moment that things
change,
especially if you're personally involved
with it.
So, so that's why that's why you uh
anicca needs to be understood in that
personal sense. As Anagarika also
pointed out, it's not like the things
that don't matter to us are impermanent.
Yeah, they're impermanent, but nobody
cares about it. The Buddhist teaching,
the Dhamma, deals with things that
matter to you
to see them as impermanent. Now, that's
the that's the practice, and obviously
that the liberation can result from
that. Because the like things that that you're
Because the like things that that you're
not involved with
emotionally with a view
you don't really care. I mean, they can
change, and anything can happen to them
will make a difference to you. And that
impermanence is not really impermanence
that results in in anatta if it's
understood, because you don't really So,
you need to take things
that your sense of self is involved with.
your sense of self is involved with.
There is a sense of self view, there is
the appropriation is mine.
And then recognizing those things
while you're holding them as mine
as being outside of the the scope
or even the possibility
of your own intentionality. What it
means fundamentally they're utterly
inaccessible. They have a They have a
reason on their
because of that, they will cease on
their own.
You your entire domain of control, sense
of ownership, everything else is
completely secondary to it and can never
be more than that.
So, that's why arahant, when he fully
understands this, he doesn't
he doesn't turn into a robot or somebody
who is not aware of his intentions. He's
just he cannot anymore misconceive his
intentions as to spill, so to speak,
into this inaccessible domain of things'
origination. He recognizes the limit, the extent of
He recognizes the limit, the extent of
possibility of control, intentional
intention, cetana, and all.
Having fully understood it, he stops
misconceiving it. Because of that, he
can still intend, think, speak, and so
on have preferences even, but none of
that can can pervert into that view of
ownership. And that's how we come come to these um
And that's how we come come to these um
inversions or perversions of perception
and view and the mind.
The point is uh everybody starts with a
self-centered experience with a sense of
self. Perversions of perception in the
mind. Uh every experience
Uh every experience
an enlightened experience starts with
with self-centeredness, with
appropriation, which means uh that's
what takes priority.
I am, thus things are mine.
Uh if a person starts to to practice and
ponder on on anicca correctly,
then it well, then the the evidence is
going to start to contradict the uh the
assumed picture of your own experience,
so that sense of self.
And that's when you start to realize
that um
um
things are mine
not because I am. It's I am because I
keep taking things as mine mistakenly.
So, that's already that's already that
perversion of ownership that that arises
on account of the uh perversion of
perception, perceiving
things that have arisen on their own
outside of the scope of your own
intention, of your own perception for
that matter,
perceiving them as if they've arisen for
you or within you.
So, so in that sense, you're already
you're already um perverting
that uh that inherent impossibility of
ownership, which is what anicca is,
as uh uh
as something that you thoroughly own.
But, the only even even that perversion
is possible to exist only because things
have arisen on their own outside of your
scope of your intention and perception.
So, that's why once once this becomes
apparent, well, then then it's
impossible. Then you don't have to go
and undo these perversions. It's not
knowing this, that's why it's perverted.
Because even that perversion cannot
escape the nature of things having
arisen outside of the scope of your
ownership. The nature of things as impermanent.
The nature of things as impermanent.
So, whether you pervert them or not,
they're impermanent. Perversion just
keeps you blind in regard to that
impermanence. Hence, when impermanence is seen
Hence, when impermanence is seen
correctly, the perversion is gone.
And the same. So, what you perceive,
that's what that's
those are the views you're going to be
developing. So, once the mind once the
perception is perverted, the views are
perverted. The assumption, the upadana.
Once the views are perverted, then the
whole experience, the whole mind is
perverted, equally perverted. So, it's
it's it's not necessarily
happening in succession as to 1 2 3.
It's more like three layers of
perversion of simultaneously
present perversion that's all rooted in
the same thing.
So, you can undo or you can understand
the principle of perversion and thus
abandon it
through either
understanding the perversion of
impermanence, understanding the perversion of um
understanding the perversion of um
self and not self, and understanding the
perversion of unattractive and
attractive. Cuz these three things share
the same principle.
Like we perceive attractive always on
the basis of unattractive, always,
entirely. There is absolutely no
exception. Like what I just said.
The perversion of perception as as
permanent it's always on account of
things having arisen on their own
beforehand. Uh and that means arisen outside of the
Uh and that means arisen outside of the
scope of your ownership or the
possibility of your ownership.
So, even the the the the factual
attractive that we perceive in the
world, it's within the scope of
unattractive, which means it's not truly
the attractive, it's more like less
unattractive but equally unattractive in
terms of sharing the same nature.
And the sense of self, the same that
comes comes what I mentioned with the
with the sense of mind.
Uh once you start undoing the sense of
mind, then you realize that this self,
which is
which has been taken to be me, to be I
am, it's actually not in my control. Why?
it's actually not in my control. Why?
Because it's fully rooted, fully
founded, fully risen upon things that
are outside of the scope of the outside
of the possibility even of the scope of
my control, my conceiving, my uh my
understanding. So, you recognize that
you discern the presence of the outside
domain of impermanence without
misconstruing it
as the inside domain, as my domain, as
for me.
So, so in that sense, that which is self
becomes not my self because you you you
cannot not see that that sense of self
is fully embedded, fully enclosed within
this outer fundamental sense of
impermanence. That it's like
That it's like
even the possibility of escape as in
having something permanent apart from
this, it's thoroughly inconceivable. Even in
it's thoroughly inconceivable. Even in
the wildest theory and imagination, you
can't even conceive it as such.
And for as long as that's not very
clear, that's how you keep conceiving it and
that's how you keep conceiving it and
giving it being in this experience of
your control, which is why you keep
feeding the sense of that that
self-centeredness, that sense of self,
the views, the uh the perversion of
perception, and so on.
So, let me just
to finish this uh
the verse. So, the verse from the same
suta of the verses So, perceiving
permanence in the impermanent,
perceiving pleasure in what is
suffering, perceiving a self in what is
not self,
perceiving attractiveness in what is
unattractive, being resolved to wrong views, their
being resolved to wrong views, their
minds deranged, their perception
twisted.
Such people are bound by the yoke of
Mara and do not teach, do not reach
security from bondage. Beings continue
in samsara, going to birth and death.
But when Buddhas arise in the world,
sending forth a brilliant light, they
will reveal this Dhamma that leads to
the stilling of suffering.
Having heard it, wise people have
regained their sanity.
They have seen the impermanent as
impermanent and they've seen suffering
as suffering. They've seen what is not
self as not self
and they've seen the unattractive as
unattractive. By the acquisition of the right view,
By the acquisition of the right view,
they have overcome all suffering.